Okay so
hi, so it's really a wonderful opportunity to be here and I
really appreciate you arranging for the lovely weather. When
I heard that I was coming to Minnesota in the winter, I
was a little trepidatious but actually it's really such a beautiful day
here and had a great opportunity to begin to get to know
some of you.
So the topic today is about מחיצה mechitzah and what I'd really
like to do, it's a pretty big source sheet here, package here.
Maybe what I could ask you to start getting this circulated around.
So we're not going to cover nearly, thank you, we're not going
to cover
nearly
all of the sources here, but hopefully they'll be available for reference
for those who want to look at more of them later. Let
me tell you what I would like to do in the time
that we have.
The issue of a מחיצה, mechitzah, some of it can be looked
at sometimes the questions one can ask is what's the source of
it, where does that come from, what are the requirements, how high
does it have to be, transparent or not transparent, opaque, when do
you need a מחיצה? mechitzah? So these are all a lot of
practical technical questions which I'll address a little bit, but there's I
think a deeper philosophical question at play here or that is informed
by how we answer some of these other questions, which is the
question about how much do we see women as part of the
congregation or not? And how much do we see a מחיצה mechitzah
and other questions relating to women's place within the synagogue as a
way of sort of defining this, saying that a synagogue is fundamentally
a male space and not really women really don't belong here, or
is there another way that we can think about the role of
מחיצה mechitzah that is not exclusionary and does not say that women
are not part of the congregation? And this question is not only
about מחיצה, mechitzah, there's other implications to this question as well. For
example, there's the question about what happens if a congregation wants to
change its setup. So they had a section that was the women's
section and now they're doing some type of architectural changes and they
want to make a part of the women's section into the men's
or part of the men's section into the women's and they're expanding
whatever they're doing. So this question comes up among some of the
פוסקים, poskim, some of the halakhic authorities, and a number of them
say well you can make a woman's section into the men's section
because that would be raising its level of sanctity. But you can't
make the men's section into the women's section because that would be
lowering its level of sanctity. Now there are others that disagree with
this, but that itself should tell us that those that take that
approach look at not just the women's section but women's sort of
presence in the synagogue in a particular way. And let me give
you another area in which this is relevant and that's the question
about do we say that it's more valuable for men, we say
that men should strive to דאוון בציבור, daven be-tzibbur, דאוון daven where
there's a מנין. minyan. Actually I'm not sure I'm allowed to let
this secret out but I will because the actual ruling of almost
all of the פוסקים poskim agree that there's not an individual obligation
to דאוון בציבור, daven be-tzibbur, meaning the community has to have a
מנין, minyan, a regular דאוונינג davening taking place and it's certainly preferred
to דאוון daven with a מנין, minyan, but it's not actually obligatory
on each individual because then everybody who דאוונס davens at home because
they have to go off to work or whatever would be somehow
not fulfilling that obligation, it really isn't obligatory on each individual, although
a number of פוסקים poskim say that you're not allowed to tell
anybody this because if you tell people this we'll never get a
מנין. minyan. So anybody who this is counterproductive to have heard that
you can ignore what I said. But we do say that it's
better for men to דאוון daven in a מנין. minyan. How about
women? Do we say that it's better for a woman to דאוון,
daven, to come to שול shul and be there for the מנין
minyan so that she can be דאוונינג davening and answering קדיש Kaddish
and קדושה, Kedushah, hearing the קריאת התורה? Kriat HaTorah? Do we say
yeah actually for woman it doesn't matter whether she comes or not?
So these are all related questions and clearly there are a number
of פוסקים poskim who feel in all of these areas that women,
their place really isn't in the synagogue. And then there are others
who disagree and actually answer that a woman's section has the same
sanctity as the men's section. A woman does get a higher fulfillment
and should be encouraged to come to synagogue just like the man
is, and in terms of מחיצה mechitzah have a different way of
understanding what מחיצה mechitzah is about and not about fundamentally defining it
as though the worship space is fundamentally a male space. So let's
talk and start the talk about the issue of מחיצה. mechitzah.
Interestingly, in the גמרא, Gemara, there is really no source source to
explicit source to the idea of a need of מחיצה mechitzah for
דאווענען. davening. We first begin to find explicit references to men and
women דאווענען davening separately in the גאוני Gaonic period where they just
mention this in passing. For example, there's a discussion about can you
accept the testimony of women if men aren't available? So when would
that come up? So this came up in a number of the
אשכנזי Ashkenazi פוסקים poskim in the time in the Middle Ages in
the time of the ראשונים Rishonim when guess what? Fighting for seats
in a synagogue, and whose seat is, who had the seat by
the Western Wall or by the Eastern Wall, excuse me, those, those
are old debates and they go back to like the 13th century,
12th century. And what happens if you had a similar fight in
the women's section? Where was this person's seat? So can you accept
the testimony of women since men were not available? Now actually there
it doesn't even refer to a women's section, it refers to the
בית כנסת לנשים. Beit Knesset l'nashim. Presumably it was in a different
structure, certainly in a different room. So just in the context of
a conversation about accepting women's testimony, we find out that women were
דאווענען davening separate from men in a separate space, and this already
we find in the גאוני Gaonic period around the 6th, 7th, maybe
8th century. In the גמרא Gemara we don't have an explicit reference
one way or the other. We don't have an explicit reference that
they were דאווענען davening together, we don't have an explicit reference they
were דאווענען davening separate. Archaeological evidence is very indeterminate. It used to
be that the archaeologists who found these old synagogues and said, oh
yes, this is the women's section until somebody pointed out, how do
you know it's the women's section? It's just a different room. You're
just assuming based on the current realities that there was a women's
section and you're labeling it as such and there really is, it's
indeterminate in terms of the archaeological evidence. But we do know minimally
from the time of the גאונים Geonim and possibly earlier. But in
the גמרא Gemara there's no explicit reference. Yes.
What about, what about in the Temple?
So we're going to get to the Temple. Okay. So we're going
to get to that in a minute, but not in the synagogue.
In the Temple there was one, we're going to get to that.
That's going to be one of these bases of this idea. Yes.
I had one question that was milling in my head is, so
men may not have an obligation to דאווען daven in a מנין,
minyan, do men have an obligation to make, help make the מנין?
minyan?
Yes. So that's seen as a communal, yes. Yes. And that's a
good point, thank you for correcting that for everybody who's thinking now
they're not going to make a מנין. minyan. It is a communal
obligation to make, to have a מנין minyan and to, and to
have קריאת התורה kriat HaTorah and to have these and to have
these, so but the, but a communal obligation as we know, it's
harder to own a communal obligation because any one person doesn't have
to be the one doing it. But yes, as especially I would
say a smaller more tight-knit community as I get a sense this
is, hopefully can really own, own that responsibility of what a communal
obligation is. Sometimes when people come together better when it's a smaller
group and everybody relies on everyone else. So it's not in the
גמרא Gemara about דאווענען davening separate, but we know that this already
goes back a good minimally as I said about 7th, 8th century.
So we're talking like a good 13, 14 hundred years and maybe
from the time of the גמרא. Gemara. It only became an issue
to need to explain what it was based on in the modern
period when we became more self-conscious of the fact that we had
men and women separate. Certainly it became an issue when even in
synagogues men and women began since the advent of the non-Orthodox movements
began to דאווען daven together. But believe it or not that was
not in Western Europe, that was only the first mixed congregation was
actually in the United States and it was actually much later than
the beginning of Reform. Reform did not begin with mixed congregations. But
nevertheless it already begins in the time of the חתם סופר, Chatam
Sofer, the 18th century, late 18th century, early 19th century and he
is explaining, he actually dealt with an interesting case that the Tsar
was coming I think to Saint Petersburg and there was a question
about whether they could have a mixed choir in the main synagogue
in Saint Petersburg sing for the Tsar. And he in the in
the context of a תשובה teshuvah of a responsum on that issue
he discusses and why is it that we don't have men and
women sitting together in the synagogue let alone singing together? That's the
first reference that we have somebody actually reflecting and trying to find
a source in the תלמוד Talmud and explain a reason for this.
So what are the reasons that are given in the last hundred
two hundred years to explain why we have men and women דאווען
daven separate in our שולס? shuls? So there are basically what I
would say three explanations. One as was stated was well that's the
way they had it in the Temple. In the Temple they had
the men's section and the women's section. So if you take a
look here in this source sheet I actually have a little diagram
to help you sort of see this is what the Temple looks
like schematic at least, okay, the Second Temple. Okay, so this part,
this was all open air except for this structure right, this was
the more like we're learning now, where we're reading now in the
תורה Torah about the משכן, mishkan, this part more
represents the משכן. mishkan. And all of this and this area here
you see says עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, the thing that looks like
a big plus sign, right? Because these are like chambers in the
corners. That's the women's courtyard. And then this where there's this black
line in the middle, there's this little section I don't know if
you could see it in small print it's עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael,
which is called the Israel section, and then it's עזרת כהנים, Ezrat
Kohanim, the next space was where the כהנים Kohanim would go. So
when there was a need to start explaining where we get this
idea, some of the פוסקים poskim turned to the model of the
Temple. Now I should actually refer to another source besides the חתם
סופר, Chatam Sofer, another event that led to the need to explain
where this is from. There actually was a famous story, a court
case involving a synagogue, and I'm trying to remember what it is,
I think it's Mount Kisco, but- Mount Clemens? Thank you. Mount Clemens.
What? Mount Clemens in Michigan. Michigan, okay, so you know this place
better than me. It's from your neck of the woods. And this
synagogue actually had in its charter that there could be, that if
any change in the sort of ritual or structure of the synagogue
that went against, that was not in keeping with הלכה, halacha, could
not be made if there were at least ten members in good
standing that did not want that change to be made. So as
we, this was in like, this was about in the 1950s or
60s, I don't remember the exact timing. This was a time when
a lot of the,
there was a lot of battle, the synagogues were a big battleground
between Orthodox and Conservative. A lot of the synagogues had a membership
that was pretty similar in terms of degrees of observance and often
had rabbis that had similar backgrounds and education. And the biggest indicator,
right, whether it was Orthodox or Conservative, and still in many ways
is the biggest indicator, was the presence or the absence of the
מחיצה. mechitzah. And therefore, when there was a desire to take down
the מחיצה, mechitzah, that was meaning that well, this synagogue is becoming
now Conservative. And that was happening in this synagogue, but ten members
said we don't want it down, we want to keep the מחיצה.
mechitzah. So the question became, well, then we can't take it down
if, assuming that the מחיצה mechitzah is a halachic requirement.
So the case, so this was actually brought to a, to the
courts, whether the, right, whether it was keeping within the charter, was
the מחיצה mechitzah a halachic requirement. So the- What? The American court
system. Not a בית דין, Beit Din, right. So the people that
wanted the מחיצה mechitzah down got a whole series of responsa from
JTS, from all the big rabbis in JTS, and all they were
collected in an edition of Conservative Judaism, the magazine, you can see
all the responsa there. And then the side that wanted to keep
it, wanted to keep the מחיצה, mechitzah, got all their, you know,
a lot of תשובות teshuvot and responsa from Rav Soloveitchik and other
great authorities and rabbis at the time, Rav Moshe Feinstein and so
on. So the Orthodox תשובות teshuvot were collected in a book called
Sanctity of the Synagogue, I don't know if anybody's ever seen this
book. And this book actually was the book that they handed out
for many years at a rabbinical school that was not mine, they
handed out for many years at the סמיכה smicha ceremony, actually, which
says a lot about how this, you know, was so much about
identifying a synagogue as Orthodox and how important this was. So as
a result of this, these great halachic authorities were solicited to write
a response saying why מחיצה mechitzah is a halachic requirement. In the
end, this went all the way to the State Supreme Court and
then I think the actual, I don't know if it actually went
to the Federal Supreme Court, I forget how it ended, but that
doesn't matter because it was a good fight and we got a
lot of interesting תשובות teshuvot written. So one of the answers, one
of the, of the sources that was given to say that מחיצה
mechitzah was required was to say that it has to be like
the Temple. That we call our synagogue a מקדש מעט, mikdash me'at,
a temple in miniature, and therefore the same way in the Temple
there was a difference between a men's section and a women's section,
so therefore in our בית כנסת beit knesset we have to have
a difference between a men's and a women's section. Now there's a
few things to unpack with this. Number one, just strictly as a
halachic argument, you know, nowhere in the תלמוד Talmud does it say
that we have to follow other aspects or any aspects of exactly
the structure, you know, the architecture of the Temple.
And so there's no, you can't make a tight halachic argument that
just because this is the way it was in the Temple, that's
required in our synagogue. There's no source that says that. But putting
even that aside, I want to focus on what the message is,
what it says, which is our real question about what מחיצה mechitzah
says about the type of space and how we understand our space.
Because if you think about it in the case, let's look for
a moment at this picture, right? In the case of this temple.
Now the women's section is huge, right? So what does this mean?
Does that mean that like there were a hundred times as many
women that came as men? What do you think it means that
you had such a large women's section here? It was mixed. Women
did not mean only women. Women actually meant even women. It was
a place for this was basically, you know what this would correspond
to? What would this correspond to? Like the, yeah, like the lobby,
the social hall. This is where everybody would go and mixed and
hang out until it was time, right? And actually as because we're
going to find out in another source, this is actually also where
they had the שמחת בית השואבה, Simchat Beit Hasho'eiva, right? That big
party that they had on סוכות, Sukkot, which is another basis for
the idea of מחיצה. Mechitza. So this was, you know, this was
the social hall, okay? This is what this was. And then when
it was time to actually bring your sacrifice, you'd cross this black
line here, which was a wall, and you'd go into the temple
proper. And that's important, because actually the sanctity of the temple, what
really halakhically is defined as the temple, is only from this black
line on. This part here was not defined as the temple. It
was actually like a lobby. It was a social hall. And therefore
the first thing that this basically is saying is if you use
this as a model, what you're basically saying is is that the
place of worship is a male space and that the place where
women are is really not the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash or it's
not the בית הכנסת, Beit HaKnesset, it's really not the place of
worship. Worship is a male space and we learn that from the
temple and that the place in which women are expected to be,
that's actually the lobby, that's not actually the מקדש. Mikdash. One second.
Now, this does not mean that women were never allowed in this
space. I'll actually read you a humorous גמרא Gemara that actually says
that women would sometimes go there. But just because women are occasionally
allowed in when they need to come in, because sometimes a woman
would have to bring her sacrifice in and so she'd have to
come in, most of the time you could send a sacrifice, but
sometimes you have to be there personally. Just because occasionally you're allowed
in doesn't change the fact that fundamentally you were saying that this
is a male space. Now actually it's even a little bit more
disturbing because a point I glossed over before was that the name
of this space is not עזרת גברים, Ezrat Gevarim, right? But what's
the name of this space? עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. Now ישראל Yisrael
could be in contrast to כהנים, Kohanim, right? It's Israelites' space as
opposed to כהנים Kohanim space, but also in contrast to עזרת נשים,
Ezrat Nashim, it's also a little bit disturbing in terms of what
is the primary community of Israel as opposed to not the primary
community. So using this as a model, even bracketing the question of
the, you know, the halakhic strength of the argument, it's a disturbing
model in terms of what it says at a deeper philosophical level
about the nature of the synagogue and the nature of the worship
space. Now I actually want to read you a humorous גמרא Gemara
about this, which would point out that women would sometimes be there
and that's the first source. Okay, so let's take a look. And
here's the first source from the גמרא Gemara in קידושין Kiddushin 52b.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, so our rabbis taught: ואחר פטירתו של רבי
מאיר, Ve-achar petirato shel Rabbi Meir, after רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir passed
away, אמר להם רבי יהודה לתלמידיו, Amar lahem Rabbi Yehuda letalmidav, so
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said to his students: אל יכנסו תלמידי רבי
מאיר לכאן, Al yikhnesu talmidei Rabbi Meir le-khan, don't let רבי מאיר's
Rabbi Meir students in the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, מפני שקנתרנים הם,
mipnei she-kantarim hem, because you know they don't have a רבי rebbe
now so they want to join our בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, מפני
שקנתרנים הם, mipnei she-kantarim hem, because they are disputatious, you know, they're
like they're troublemakers, ולא ללמוד תורה הם באים, velo lilmod Torah hem
ba'im, they're not really seeking true knowledge, they just want to like
show off how smart they are, אלא לקפחני בהלכות הם באים, ela
le-kapekhni bahalakhot hem ba'im, they're trying to you know to overwhelm me
or to demonstrate how smart they are. דחק סומכוס ונכנס, Dachak Sumkhus
venikhnas, now one of רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir prize students, סומכוס, Sumkhus,
forced his way into the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. Remember that phrase
דחק ונכנס dachas venikhnas it's going to come up later. אמר להם,
Amar lahem, he said to them: כך שנו לי רבי מאיר, Kakh
shanu li Rabbi Meir, this is what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir taught
me: המקדש בחלקו, Ha-mekadesh be-khelko, if a man marries a woman with
his portion in the sacrifices—so you had this meat that you had
from a sacrifice you brought and you are now going and now
you the man are going to give it to a woman and
say marry me, not with this lovely ring but marry me with
this nice steak. Okay, so בין קדשי קדשים בין קדשים קלים לא
קידש, bein kodshei kodashim bein kodashim kalim lo kidesh,
whether it is the holiest of sacrifices or the less weighty of
sacrifices, he's not married because it's not really his. You eat the
meat of the sacrifice, but it's not really yours, you don't really
own it. Okay, so that's what he taught. כעס רבי יהודה עליהם,
Ka'as Rabbi Yehuda aleihem, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda got angry on his
students. אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said: לא כך אמרתי לכם, Lo
kakh amarti lakhem, didn't I tell you this? אל יכנסו מתלמידי רבי
מאיר לכאן, Al yikhnesu mitalmidei Rabbi Meir le-khan, don't let רבי מאיר's
Rabbi Meir students come in here. מפני שקנתרנים הם, Mipnei she-kantarim hem,
troublemakers, ולא ללמוד תורה הם באים אלא לקפחני בהלכות הם באים, velo
lilmod Torah hem ba'im ela le-kapekhni bahalakhot hem ba'im, they're coming to
show me up. וכי אשה בעזרה מניין? Ve-khi isha ba-azarah minayin? What's
a woman doing in the—how could you marry a woman with your
sacrifice if it's the holy of—if it's the holiest sacrifices, they can't
be taken out of the עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, they can't even
be taken into the עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. So how could a
man be marrying a woman with his steak from his sacrifice if
he—what would a woman be doing there? So obviously this is just
a mind game, this is not a real case. אמר רבי יוסי,
Amar Rabbi Yosi, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says, יאמרו, Yomru, people
would say מאיר שכב, Meir shachav, מאיר Meir passed away, רב מאיר.
Reb Meir. יהודה כעס, Yehuda ka'as, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda got
angry at one of his students. יוסי שתק, Yosi shatak, and I
should stand by silently? דבר תורה מה תהא עליה? Dvar Torah mah
teha aleha? Who's going to defend the honor of Torah? You know,
רב מאיר, Reb Meir, this is not, this is real Torah of
רב מאיר. Reb Meir. Somebody has to defend. So here's how I'm
going to answer what, how a man could marry a woman in
the עזרה, Azara, in the main section of the Temple. וכי אין
אדם עשוי לקבל קידושין לבתו בעזרה? V'chi ein adam asui l'kabel kiddushin
l'vito b'azara?
Maybe the guy gave it to an underage girl's father, right, because
a man, a father can marry off his daughter. So you can
get men, only men involved in the קידושין. kiddushin. Who needs the
woman? You just have the father marrying her off. Or here's another
scenario. ואין אישה עשויה לעשות שליח לקבל קידושיה בעזרה? V'ein isha asuya
la'asot shaliach l'kabel kiddusheha b'azara?
Maybe the woman made somebody her agent, made a man her agent,
so it was again a transaction between men, the one representing her
side was a man. I actually was at a wedding once, which
was so פרום, frum, it was actually somebody who's a friend of
mine who normally I don't think this would normally have been the
wedding he would have expected for himself, but based on the family
he was marrying into, it was, I don't know if you've been
to weddings like this, they even have the place cards for the
men and the women on different tables, at different entrances, right, everything
is separate. I was at that wedding with David Shatz, Dr. David
Shatz, he's a big Jewish philosopher and he's also like a real,
very funny guy. Anyway, so we're talking and standing and שמוזינג, shmoozing,
and he said, "this wedding is so פרום, frum, I don't know
if I'm allowed to have mixed feelings."
So that was great. So anyway, so there we are at this
wedding and up there under the חופה, chuppah, right, is everybody who
walks up is this guy with like a big black suit, black
hat, right, at the end of the whole procession there are like
twenty guys in black suits up there and this one little כלה,
kallah, you know, overwhelmed by all of these men. So the other
guy sitting next to me, not David Shatz, but anyway, he said,
"you know, if they really wanted to be פרום, frum, she would
have just made her brother like a שליח shaliach and then it
could have been like all men up there." So that's what, so
that's what we're saying over here, right? Why didn't she go ahead?
So, it could have been a man she could do קידושין kiddushin
in the עזרה Azara without any women, okay. And but now here's
the last answer, and he says: ועוד דחקה ונכנסה שמא. V'od dachaka
v'nichnasa shema. Let's say she forced her way in. She pushed her,
pushed through. So maybe she is in the עזרה. Azara. Now of
course that echoes back the fact that סומכוס Sumchus forced his way
into the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. Okay, so it's a nice little
story, but what it shows is that even though women might be
allowed to be there, and then that's a, I'm not getting into
the details, it's a discussion about when exactly women would come, when
they would, when it was necessary they would be allowed. Fundamentally, the
גמרא Gemara can't imagine that that's a normal scenario that a woman
would be there. It's basically a male space. Okay, now it's a
big enough challenge to explain that in terms of the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, but you know, for the most part,
I mean, there's enough things to worry about in terms of like
the right, you know, the here and now, that I don't spend,
we just got to פורים, Purim, you know, how do you explain
עמלק, Amalek, how is that moral and ethical, and those are serious
questions that have to be dealt with, how do you deal with
קרבנות korbanot and animal sacrifices, but you know, I think that I
tend to focus more on like the issues that really demand our
attention. I'd much rather spend the time worrying about like the עגונה
agunah problem than worrying about the עמלק Amalek problem. So, we have
enough of a problem, I'm saying, it is a problem anyway understanding
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that is what it was, it was
fundamentally a male space. But that doesn't mean that we have to
import that model and say that that's the basis of why we
think we need a מחיצה mechitzah for our synagogue. I'll take questions
in a second, I just want to say, and this, having this
as the model, in addition to the I think disturbing philosophical religious
point it's making, can also have a practical implication. I was once
giving a lecture similar to this, and a woman said to me,
got up and said, "you know, in my synagogue we were, it
was I think it was a new synagogue or we were restructuring
it, redesigning it, and this question was where was the מחיצה mechitzah
going to go?" And I wanted it to go down the middle
or at least at the sides, and the rabbi says "No, it
has to be in the back, just like the way it was
in the בית המקדש." Beit HaMikdash. So the women have to be
in the back, they can't even be along the sides, right? And
obviously that really pushes women outside of the synagogue. Yes, there was
a hand up, yes.
So two things, the first of which is the other way to
look at this גמרא Gemara is that רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, if
they pushed their way in, doesn't feel he has the authority to
push them out.
Right, aha, right, so that's right. So a woman may, it might
be if she gets her way in, she has a right to
be there for why she's there, right.
In other words, in the end, he's conceding that,
right, right.
Yeah, that is a good point, you know, and I agree, it's
sort of saying like, you know, people can have a legitimacy to
be in a space even if you don't want them there, right.
But still, it doesn't change the fact that it was basically רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, and it doesn't change the
fact that it basically is still a male space even if there
was a legitimate reason for a woman to sometimes be there. So
this is one model. That's a model that רב קוק Rav Kook
sort of references. If you take a look here on page three,
we'll just read one sentence from this. This is one of the
responsa collected in this book, Sanctity of the Synagogue, and he says
like this in the first paragraph, again, I'm only reading very selectively.
According to the Talmud, the synagogues are to be looked on as
the sacred temple in miniature. It's therefore our duty to exalt them
to the same level of holiness as our holy temple, may it
be rebuilt in our day. Our fathers in establishing two separate divisions
for men and women, thereby continuing the system inaugurated in the temple
and using that as the model. So that is one model. As
I said, I find that a very challenging model. Now, there's another
Talmudic passage which serves as the basis for the other two models.
Yes.
So there's a historical reference that's even older than the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, which is if you look at אז ישיר. Az Yashir.
Yes. It's clear that the men sang and מרים Miriam with the
women sang separately. So this notion that the men and women being
separate dates back even to...
Right, I mean, again, that's, you know, that's for singing, but and
so, but you're right. I mean, it's an interesting question about using
that as the model for a מחיצה. Mechitza.
I haven't seen that as a general rule, mostly I think because
it doesn't deal with the physical structure. And you do have to
understand that part of it was, you know, some שולס, shuls, and
even today there's I think one remaining Orthodox שול shul that's a
member of the OU that has separate sections without a מחיצה Mechitza
down the middle. But you know, and that was but part of
it was there were two issues: mixed seating, and then separate sitting
but also that there should be a מחיצה. Mechitza. But you are
right, you know, it's interesting that that I have not seen that
source used more. But that doesn't at least address like a physical
barrier. So the other source that's used is another passage about the
temple. And this is the passage about what I referred to before,
the שמחת בית השואבה, Simchas Beis HaShoeiva, the big parties that they
would have on חול המועד סוכות, Chol HaMoed Sukkot, you know, leading
up all through the night, leading up to the ritual of drawing
the water and pouring the libations on the altar. And it said
they would do these youth parties and it said that they kept
the men and women separate. Okay. And that is and it actually
speaks about them building a structure to divide the men and the
women. So let's take a look at that passage because this is
the other major source that is pointed to to be for the
basis of a מחיצה. Mechitza. And here's what it says in source
number four from סוכה Sukkah 51b. Okay. במוצאי יום טוב, B'motzaei Yom
Tov, when יום טוב Yom Tov was over, the first night, they
would go and they would make a big set things up. מאי
תיקון גדול? Mai Tikkun Gadol? What was the big things that they
would set up? אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, כאותה ששנינו k'osah
she-shoninu like we talked. חלקה היתה בראשונה, Chalaka hay'sa barishona, the עזרת
נשים Ezras Nashim was used was flat. והקיפוה גזוסטרא, Ve-hikifuha gezustra, and
they surrounded it with a גזוסטרא. gezustra. Interesting question, does that mean
a balcony, or does that mean like a like a מחיצה, Mechitza,
like a type of a protrusion, you know, so that becomes a
question about whether the women were on a higher level or were
they behind some type of a division. והתקינו שיהיו נשים יושבות מלמעלה
ואנשים מלמטה. Ve-hiskinu she-yehu nashim yoshvos milma'ala ve-anashim milmata.
So this very much sounds like it's a balcony because it said
the women were above and the men below. And now we have
another story, another version of this. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis
taught. בראשונה היו נשים מבפנים ואנשים מבחוץ. Barishona hayu nashim mibifnim ve-anashim
mibachutz.
Originally, the women were on the inside, maybe closer to the actual,
you know, temple section itself, and the men were on the outside.
והיו באים לידי קלות ראש, Ve-hayu ba'in lidei kalus rosh, and it
would lead to, you know, improper mixing, because I guess if a
woman had to get to her section, she'd have to cut through
the men's section. התקינו שיהיו נשים יושבות מבחוץ ואנשים מבפנים. Hiskinu she-yehu
nashim yoshvos mibachutz ve-anashim mibifnim. So the men were on the outside.
ועדיין היו באים לידי קלות ראש. Ve-adayin hayu ba'in lidei kalus rosh.
Same problem. Now a man has to get to his section, he
cuts through the women's section. התקינו שיהיו נשים יושבות מלמעלה ואנשים מלמטה.
Hiskinu she-yehu nashim yoshvos milma'ala ve-anashim milmata. The women were above and
the men were below. Okay, now, so they separated them. So the
גמרא Gemara says: היכי עבדי הכי? Heichi avdi hachi? How could you
make a structural change in the temple? והא כתיב, Ve-ha ksiv, the
verse says: הכל בכתב מיד ה' עלי השכיל. Hakol bichtav miyad Hashem
alai hiskil. דוד David says: The whole structure of the temple was
revealed to me by God, so presumably we can't change it. Which
is pretty ironic because the second temple was changed different than the
first temple. But okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers. אמר
רב, Amar Rav, קרא אשכח ודרש. kra ashkech ve-darash. They found the
following verse. וספדה הארץ משפחות משפחות לבד. V'safda ha'aretz mishpachos mishpachos l'vad.
This is prophesying the end of times when the Messianic times when
they will now cry over the death of a figure that is
well-known in Kabbalistic literature but not so well-known in popular imagination, which
is משיח בן יוסף, Mashiach ben Yosef, a descendant
from the tribe of יוסף Yosef that will lead them into war
and he'll die in war. And then משיח בן דוד Mashiach ben
David will be the king. So it says that they'll eulogize his
death, משפחת בית דוד לבד ונשיהם לבד. mishpachas beis David l'vad un'sheihem
l'vad. The family of דוד David by themselves and their wives separate.
So there is another men and women separate. אמרו, Amru, and they
said: והלא דברים קל וחומר. V'halo devarim kal vachomer. We can make
an argument from a weak to a strong case. ומה לעתיד לבוא,
U'mah l'asid lavo, in the
future, שעוסקים בהספד, she-oskim ba-hesped, first of all, they're eulogizing, so it's
not a time of levity, it's a time of seriousness. ואין יצר
הרע שולט בהם, Ve-ein yetzer hara sholeit bahem, and also like the
the power of the the lustful drives doesn't isn't overtaking them, a)
because it's a eulogy and b) presumably Messianic times, it's less of
a concern. אמר תורה אנשים לבד ונשים לבד, Amar Torah anashim levad
venashim levad, you have to keep men and women
separate, עכשיו שעוסקים בשמחה ויצר הרע שולט בהם, achshav she-oskim besimcha veyetzer
hara sholet bahem, now that we're involved in all this levity and
joy and people do have their natural types of sexual urges, על
אחת כמה וכמה, al achat kama vekama, how much more so we
have to keep men and women separate. And therefore they kept men
and women separate during the שמחת בית השואבה. Simchat Beit Hashoeva. Is
this a good basis for saying why we need a מחיצה mechitza
in שול? shul? What do you think? Is this relevant to the
question? No? Some people say yes. Why do you say no?
Because here they're talking about the party time.
Right, it's having a big party.
You should have in the social hall, then you have a separation.
Right, they didn't keep the men and women separate normally in the
social hall, right? It was on the rest of the year, we
already discussed that the עזרת נשים ezrat nashim was the place that
men and women were both present until it was time to go
in. So they only did the separation during the שמחת בית השואבה,
Simchat Beit Hashoeva, so maybe at a time of a party, that's
when you need it separate. Yes?
I would argue yes, exactly. Yes, if you already have to separate
men and women in a time of partying, then certainly in a
more serious שול shul you should have them separate.
Okay, so you could go both ways. You could say, if you're
doing something as serious in שול shul you need to be more
focused and not as distracted and so on, but you could also
say maybe if it's that type of serious-mindedness, maybe there isn't concern
about the environment
leading to creating a disturbing environment as it was when people are
in the middle of partying. So you could argue both ways. Some
want to say, well we can point to what I thought you
were going to say was, well it says that even at the
time of the funeral they would be separate. So clearly even at
very sort of serious somber times you have to be separate. But
the problem is that the גמרא Gemara is either too narrow or
too broad. If we focus on the party example, then all we
would know is, you could argue logically other cases, but all we
would know for sure is that at a time of parties you
shouldn't have mixed dancing, okay, you shouldn't have mixed parties. That was
the גמרא's Gemara concern. If you want to point to the issue
of the funeral, then we're going to get to a conclusion
that at all times you have to keep men and women separate.
Now there are חרדי Haredi communities that do that, that think you
can't even go to a lecture and see, right, everybody here would
have to be on different sides of the מחיצה, mechitza, right? Because
even at a serious time and we're all serious purpose-minded and so
on, nevertheless if at a funeral you have to keep it separate
you have to keep them separate at all times. So this is
the problem using this גמרא Gemara as the source. It's either too
narrow or too broad. So the way it gets to be applied
to the idea of the synagogue is what the חתם סופר, Chatam
Sofer, who I referred to before, does to make the bridge. If
he says that you need to keep men and women separate when
you are doing a type of a religious activity that you're directing
your words or your thoughts to God. And therefore you don't want
your thoughts to be distracted by sexual thoughts. So that's prayer. How
about this case? He says, well, rejoicing on שמחת בית השואבה Simchat
Beit Hashoeva wasn't just rejoicing. The verse says you should rejoice before
God for seven days, ושמחתם לפני השם אלקיכם שבעת ימים, usmachtem lifnei
Hashem Elokeichem shivat yamim, on סוכות. Sukkot. So it was a type
of a prayer and a joy that was being given to God.
And that's why it was a problem of having this type of
a mixed environment. And at a funeral as well, if you say
a eulogy, you sort of also there's a sense of a prayer
there as well. So he tries to take these cases, prayer,
eulogy, שמחת בית השואבה, Simchat Beit Hashoeva, and say what it means
is you can see how
he's trying to tailor it to apply to the current practice of
מחיצה mechitza because as I said we have a well-known practice that's
been with us for like fifteen hundred years at least, but we
don't have a clear source. So he's sort of tailoring this source
and saying if it's about directing your words and thoughts to God,
that's where you need a מחיצה. mechitza. And this becomes the second
source. Yes?
So Rabbi, since this is the case, how come that in many
eulogies that I've been at they don't keep men and women
separate? Right, so again, because people are inconsistent for the most part.
And I have to tell you as a person when people ask
me שאלות, sheilot, I have a real challenge in terms of פסקנינג,
paskening, I mean I do פסק pasken מחיצה mechitza questions, but normally
the way I know you go about פסקנינג paskening is you start
from all the sources in the גמרא Gemara and all the different
ways the commentaries and so on, whereas here it really started from
a practice that then went back and tried to source itself in
the גמרא. Gemara. So having a sense of consistency in how to
apply the rule
doesn't happen in the same way that you would normally expect.
So I want to now just for a moment say so that
was the second source, but what I want to do is point
to the bigger question that we were asking, which is what does
it say at a deeper level about women and their place in
the synagogue. And here there are two ways you can jump off
of that source, what the חתם סופר Chatam Sofer did and what
רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein does. What the חתם סופר Chatam
Sofer does is he says what is the problem? Okay, so somehow
that source is going to apply to דאוונען, davening, fine. But what's
the problem? So he says the problem is that men see women
and they have sexual thoughts. And therefore that's distracting the men when
they're דאווענען. davenen. And therefore you have to put up the מחיצה
mechitza to keep them separate. Now, that number one really focuses all
on the men, right? It's the men and their דאווענען davenen and
their thoughts that need to be kept sort of pure and that
we're concerned about. It's interesting, this is a whole other lecture at
a different time. I wrote an op-ed in the New York Times
once on about this what I'm about to say and there's a
copy out there, which is why the תלמוד Talmud focuses on men's
and men's sexual thoughts and not on women, you know, and
and there's a lot of issues involved in that and sort of
in how women are sort of, you know, seen in a particular
way in the תלמוד Talmud and men are seen in also the,
you know, very much in a different type of way. But that's
what he says. And therefore, the result is, is that it basically
says, we care, we want to make sure the men's prayer is
not distracted, women are creating a problem, and because men see the
women and what we have to do is, if women create the
problem, what do we have to do to the women? Make them
invisible, right? Because by seeing them, they're creating a problem for the
men, so they have to be made invisible. Women, either we don't
care about their prayer or, say it more positive way, we care
about their prayer, but we're not concerned that they'll have sexual thoughts
by looking at men, because that's a certain attitude, you know, in
in the תלמוד Talmud about like as I referred to before. And
therefore, the problem is men seeing the women, the women are the
problem, and therefore we're going to make the women not visible. And
as a result, the חתם סופר Chasam Sofer basically rules that that
the מחיצה mechitza requirement must be, ideally, there's ceiling to floor, floor
to ceiling, but certainly they have to be full height, women have
to be completely not able to be seen at all. And actually,
some, you know, the חתם סופר Chasam Sofer was the authority for
Hungarian Jewry, and a Hungarian, there are Hungarian Jews who refuse to
דאווען daven in a synagogue with a balcony, because a balcony is
the worst, because a balcony you can see, you know, you have
great sight, you can see them all, you can, you know, you
can see everyone. So therefore, it's all about not being able to
see. So again, here's an approach which basically says, it's about the
concern is about the men, women are the problem, we make them
invisible, and therefore it also translates into very strict requirements in terms
of what is needed for a מחיצה. mechitza. The third approach, and
the one that I, you know, I resonate with and I embrace,
is the approach of רב משה פיינשטיין. Rav Moshe Feinstein. Where רב
משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein says is he says it's not about
men having improper sexual thoughts. He says it's about the difference between
a single-sex space and a co-ed space. And he says, he says
it's about not about sexual הרהור, hirhur, sexual thought, it's about קלות
ראש, kalus rosh, the type of way that the environment is different
when it's a co-ed space as opposed to a single-sex. Now, what
exactly this means, I'll offer the following, you know, and I'm not
sure this is, I admit that what I'm about to say is
I think a variation of רב משה, Rav Moshe, not exactly what
רב משה Rav Moshe is saying, but I'll take it to the
following step, which is, you know, there's a whole discussion in education,
which is better, right? Single-sex education or co-ed education? Does anybody know
what pretty much the consensus is about that?
Same sex for is better for for girls, and single-sex, no, same,
yeah, and mixed,
co-ed is better for boys. Why? Because what happens is as soon
as you're in a co-ed environment, you become more self-conscious. So the
boys, if they're all by themselves, you know, they'll act like וילדע
חיות, vilde chayas, you know, they'll get out of hand, right? If
you put them with girls, forget even at a young age, even
if not about thinking about sex or anything, they'll be more self-conscious,
you know, it's more a social setting and self-conscious about their behavior
and they'll rein themselves in a little bit. With the girls, same
thing happens, but it has the deleterious effect, because when girls are
around boys, right, they've been socialized to be less assertive, to speak
up less, right, to be more, you know, to be quieter, and
if you take the boys away and they're less self-conscious, then they
are more assertive and they actually learn better in that type of
an environment. So I think you can translate that in similar ways
to what רב משה Rav Moshe is saying, which is, you know,
that when we are in a דאווענען, davenen, a phrase that רב
סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik I think used in a similar context was, we
want it to be a vertical experience, not a horizontal experience, right?
We want it to be, now the reality is we all know
שול shul is often very much a horizontal experience, like you get
together with people you haven't seen and you שמועס shmooze and it's
social. Okay, but ideally, you want to sort of be focusing on
God and not sort of be self-conscious about how you're being seen
by other people. And therefore, a single-sex, at least this is the
way the argument goes, whether this resonates with you or not, that
a single-sex environment is better for creating that type of a space
and consciousness and mindset than a co-ed environment, both for men and
for women. So it's not about women as the source of sexual
thoughts for men and women as the problem, it's about we want
a single-sex space as opposed to a co-ed space. Now, it's possible
you'll disagree with this, you know, you'll say that actually for guys
because it's single-sex, it becomes like a men's club and they, you
know, and they שמועס shmooze and they שמועס shmooze less if they
were with their families. or we actually it may be
sometimes if in other areas of our lives we're in coed spaces
and we're not so self-conscious it actually would feel totally natural in
the שול. shul. All of this might be, I'm not promising you
that this explanation is going to sort of resonate with you at
a deep level, but at least what it's doing is it's not
saying it's a male space. It's not saying we care about men's
דאווענינג, davening, women are the problem. It's saying we want a separate
sex space, we don't want a coed space. And I should say
that that also translates, and then I'll take the question, into more
inclusive requirements that רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein gives. So רב
משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein for example says that the מחיצה mechitza
does not have to be full height. The מחיצה's mechitza enough that
it's shoulder height because that's enough to create a separate type of
a space. You don't need to make the other side invisible. רב
משה Rav Moshe says actually a balcony is great because you know
even though everybody can see everybody but it keeps them as separate
spaces. And רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein also would say it
doesn't have to be totally opaque because again it's not about seeing
it's just about designating as separate spaces. So an approach that at
a philosophical level is more inclusive also at a practical level translates
into more inclusive types of criteria. Yes, there was a question.
Hello, first of all רב משה Rav Moshe said it cannot be
too low because then it becomes meaningless.
Right, I said shoulder height, shoulder height.
He says shoulder height. רב משה Rav Moshe says eighteen טפחים tefachim
which depending on how big a טפח tefach is translates into eighteen
טפחים tefachim translates into between fifty-four inches and seventy-two inches depending on
how big you think a טפח tefach is. רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik
said fifty inches, okay?
No but the question is but both both
approaches are basically a מעקה ma'akeh it's not a it's not thou
shalt not there's no direct prohibition to do so it's just that
you may come to it it's it's...
Oh
you mean it's a protective. Right it's well and that's correct but
it's speaking about the type of space and environment we are trying
to create informed by the concerns about what a different type of
a space would be.
But it would imply that if you happen to be in a
space where it is
just mixed you could still pray. Right so what you're pointing to
is and this is also worth noting you know is that when
these fights took place like you know in the 50s 60s and
beyond about you know having the מחיצה mechitza not having it,
sometimes the פוסקים poskim would actually concede and they say look it's
really might not be strict הלכה halacha it's a מנהג minhag it's
a מנהג minhag that we've had for at least fifteen hundred years
if not longer but it's something that really at a deep level
defines a our understanding about what the דאווענינג davening space is and
therefore you know it's deeply deeply ingrained in our understanding of the
type of space we want for דאווענען davening and what I would
say particularly nowadays also is that it's such it remains such a
marker of a שול's shul like Orthodox identity you know and and
we have to acknowledge that and we have to acknowledge that that's
a you know that that's a very important and critical part about
the issues around the מחיצה. mechitza. Which let me just say one
more thing about that which gets to interesting questions about when you're
not dealing with a שול. shul. You're taking a group of kids
out on a on a you know a field trip right and
you have to דאווען daven מנחה. mincha. What do you do? Do
you have to erect a מחיצה? mechitza? No I mean you create
a separate space but you don't need to put up a מחיצה
mechitza right? Or you're in a שבעה shiva house so sometimes if
possible like the women maybe will go like on a different you
know floor level or something or at a wedding but if it's
not possible you know you just have people in separate spaces without
actually erecting the מחיצה mechitza which reflects a reality that we understand
how important מחיצה mechitza is in terms of the identity of the
שול shul and there we would never not have a מחיצה mechitza
right? In other contexts now we still do insist on separate on
separate but we
but we don't insist on a מחיצה mechitza to the same degree.
Yes. But you can but you can do your own תפילה tefilla
you can
דאווען daven in a environment where there are men and women present.
So you know it's an interesting question like here you are you're
at a I don't know you're you're at a conference and you
know or you're at a wedding and there's men and women milling
around. Do you have to go to a different room or
can you sort of like go off to a corner and still
in the larger space there are men and women present. Or you're
by yourself and you're in the in the airport. Right exactly. And
you're absolutely correct because what it winds up being is and you're
saying it very very accurately that if it's just a concern that
you might have types of thought or whatever you know it might
be possible to address it so we wind up defining it as
not to have a mixed prayer experience but if you're דאווענינג davening
by yourself and there's a there's you know there's a mixed group
of people milling around it actually is better than if you're having
a group of people that are praying in a mixed setting. So
but you're absolutely correct to sort of put your finger on that.
Yes. So along the lines of inclusive in a different way I
heard this from... how family focused many congregations are and
that she felt
excluded now because so much energy seemed to be around couples, around
couples with children. That's a nice perspective. And she said that she
finally appreciated the egalitarian, ironically, nature of a מחיצה mechitza because now
she
was within a sisterhood and her status didn't matter. That's really, I
really appreciate that. I had never thought of it from that perspective
and I really appreciate that. So that's really excellent, you know. And
I should also say, you know, by the way, that it's also
not just about like the issue of height is important, but it's
also a question about about where it's situated, right? This one is
situated pretty much like down the center, right? You have often in
the back or on the sides, and that also sends certain messages.
You know the שול shul that I'm privileged to דאווען daven at,
which is the Hebrew Institute of Riverdale, you know Rabbi Weiss said
that the the that what he wants was is a שול shul
that if you walk in when it's not the time of דאווענען,
davening, you can't tell which is the men's side and the women's
side. And the way he does it is that he has it
straight down the middle and then he has the בימה bima on
like an island by itself surrounded by its own מחיצה mechitza and
then and you really can't tell, it's completely parallel. It's not always
possible to do that, but I think you know places try to
approximate that and that also, you know, is very important, yes. And
and just actually now thinking for the first time the implications of
this egalitarian nature of מחיצה, mechitza, it equally applies to men. Right.
Because status, married status or not. Right. I mean it's it's in
flux right now. So you can argue that it doesn't sound, I
mean it's designalizing because it actually applies equally. Right. The one problem
that we should acknowledge and it's not a minor problem, it's you
know it is, that it's possible true you could have a מחיצה
mechitza straight down the middle, you know we say it's not about
you know treating women different, it's about separate sex base, but at
the end of the day, right, if men still are the ones
that are leading the דאווענען davening and having all of the participatory
roles, it's hard that מחיצה mechitza doesn't get seen in that light.
And that's certainly part of the challenge. Yes. Something I'm struggling with
a little bit is this whole notion of the role of מחיצה
mechitza for levity and the specificity of that. Uh-huh. And I guess
the analogy about mixed-sex desegregation is that it sort of starts with
basically justifications that are just empirical observations. Right. Right. And levity, like
we don't have, I'm just trying to think, we don't have a
randomized control trial. Right, right. Right, right. But we would tentatively say
this is this is some postulation about yeah, we think that status
or focus going to the מחיצה mechitza have different implications for levity
versus just having sex segregated. Right. So you're absolutely correct. I mean
what I sort of set out at the beginning is is that
this if you know is that this is a practice that's been
with us for a long time. And now we have to, because
we have to be sort of self-conscious about it and start articulating
to ourselves, to others what is it about, we A look for
sources in the גמרא Gemara and we look for conceptual explanations and
you know but I'm saying that it's it's retrofitting it in, right?
It's fine and and you're absolutely correct, it's not like we did,
in general when the גמרא Gemara sometimes does look at social realities
and comes up with rulings, question about how much empirical study did
they do, but this certainly isn't that, you know. But what I
would say is let's at least given that we have these different
models, given that for American Jewry רב משה Rav Moshe Feinstein was
like the major authority, let's embrace this position and be conscious about
the implications of what it means to embrace this as opposed to
embrace another one. So but you're absolutely correct, I wouldn't make this
argument as though it logically derives from the sources or from the
empirical evidence, yes.
So would you say that רב משה's Rav Moshe answer suggests some
sort of, it sounds to me like it would allow for cultural
definitions of what feels like a separation, such as for example a
wide aisle.
Right.
So that's a good question and you know רב משה Rav Moshe
was actually asked this, right, about like why can't you have a
very wide aisle? Or why can't you have just ten טפחים, tefachim,
which is actually just like about three feet, which normally for other
הלכות halakhot is defined enough to define separate spaces? So as far
as that actually there are some פוסקים poskim like רב יהודה הרצל
הנקין Rav Yehuda Herzl Henkin who actually says that ten טפחים, tefachim,
three feet would suffice. And there have been a few שולס shuls
that actually do do have that and that is an opinion out
there that that's enough to define separate spaces. רב משה Rav Moshe
says it is about the practical feeling of the space, so that's
too low. But a big gap should be enough and actually in
principle there actually have been a few Orthodox שולס, shuls, again they
are fewer and fewer that are now members, you know, because in
the end the מחיצה mechitza becomes obviously the standard for the standard
for all, you know, Orthodox שולס, shuls, but there have been a
few that have had like a, like I think it was like
about a thirty-foot aisle or something and that have not, you know,
huge aisle. And but you're right. Look, again, what all of these
wind up being is is, you know, is retrofitted arguments. And can
you always make it was like similar questions about, you know, about
do you need it here and do you need it here and
how come at funerals we sit together? And that's why I find
it as I said frustrating as a Rabbi to פסקן pasken these
questions because the what we do doesn't always logically flow from any
one particular argument. Sometimes it's an amalgam. I wanted to I'll take
the other question in a minute but I wanted to also make
another important point, which is, you know, a lower מחיצה mechitza in
some ways is more inclusive, but, you know, in other ways it
it maybe it's it's not true that everybody wants it even if
it's a more, you know, inclusive-minded type of a community. On the
one hand, I have to tell you that I was once at
לימוד, Limmud, which is, you know, where they bring, like they have
לימוד Limmud New York and לימוד Limmud UK, and they bring together
huge like thousands of Jews and the from a, you know, from
a hundred-mile radius and all different types of learning experiences over the
weekend. And they have like seven different מניינים minyanim going. So I
went to the to the מחיצה mechitza מניין minyan and the מחיצה
mechitza they had was like eight feet high or something. It was
crazy and I'm looking around, I'm saying like the people here I
can't imagine anybody, you know, wants this, but I don't know, like
I don't want to if somebody wants a high מחיצה, mechitza, I
don't want to be imposing on it. So I get up and
I say, would anybody like have a problem if I lowered the
because it was one of the things that had notches, right? Would
anybody have a problem if I lowered the מחיצה? mechitza? So it's
like there's this uneasy silence and then one woman says, please. So
then I went and I lowered it. But at another time I
will tell you that I was we were at a certain event
and someone said, actually, you know, I I don't like to feel
that men can be looking at me when I'm דאווענינג. davening. I
want to be able to get into my דאווענינג, davening, to feel
I'm connecting to God, to not have to be self-conscious. So it
gets to that issue of self-consciousness, but here, think, that's a problem
if the מחיצה mechitza is lower. So actually what I have done
sometimes, I mean it depends on where the, you know, what people
want, is you have different sections of the מחיצה. mechitza. You have
a high section and a low section and people can sit where
they feel more comfortable. So, you know, it's also appreciating that even
if we're thinking we're being more inclusive, it doesn't mean that everybody's,
you know, people have different sensibilities around these around these issues. There
was another question, yes.
Two. The first question is, that is exact at the previous
synagogue that many members were part of when they designed the sanctuary
space, they specifically put the מחיצה mechitza in the back for the
very reason that the women didn't want the men to be looking
at them or forced them to turn around. Interesting. My other question
is in the sort of because Reform developed largely in the אשכנזי
Ashkenazi world, right, has there been some form of ספרדי Sefardic response
to מחיצה? mechitza?
You know, it's an interesting question. I have to admit that, you
know, it's it's it's a fascinating almost anomaly that because normally
we assume the social reality has been that women have in
אשכנזי Ashkenazi societies have played more you know,
more empowered roles in society than in ספרדי Sefardic societies. And therefore
we might expect that, you know, אשכנזי Ashkenazi פסק psak would be
more inclusive for women. And it often is. Like for example, if
a woman takes a לולב, Lulav, an אשכנזי Ashkenazi woman, she makes
a ברכה. Bracha. For a ספרדי Sefardi woman takes a לולב, Lulav,
she doesn't make a ברכה. Bracha. And that's huge because I remember
once I was at somebody's house, some ספרדים Sefardim on סוכות Sukkos
and I took the לולב Lulav and the, you know, the woman
of the house was there and I said, do you would you
like to take לולב? Lulav? You know, and here's the לולב Lulav
and אתרוג Esrog right here. She said, no, why would I want
to do that? You know, we don't realize that if you're not
making a ברכה, Bracha, it basically says this is a meaningless act
for me. It's the making of the ברכה Bracha that signals that
this is actually a מצוה. mitzvah. So it's a huge difference.
But interestingly, רב עובדיה יוסף Rav Ovadia Yosef actually has many more
unproblematic פסקים psakim for women's issues than אשכנזי Ashkenazi פוסקים poskim because
he's not dealing with the reality of Reform Judaism. So when there
was a whole question about can we have a בת מצוה Bat
Mitzvah ceremony, I don't know if people still remember when forty, fifty
years ago בת מצוה Bat Mitzvah ceremony even not that long ago
was a huge deal, right, within the Orthodox community. Oh my God,
you're copying from Reform and Conservative Judaism. You know, רב עובדיה Rav
Ovadia says, says, of course you can have a בת מצוה Bat
Mitzvah ceremony. Why is it any different than a בר מצוה? Bar
Mitzvah? And it'll get people more involved in their Judaism and you
know it'll bring more people in. Why should you not do it?
Can a woman make ברכת הגומל Birkat HaGomel in שול? shul? So,
you know, the אשכנזי Ashkenazi פוסק, posek, it's so complicated. רב עובדיה
Rav Ovadia says, of course they can, why shouldn't they be able
to? So in an interesting and ironic way because he's not dealing
with responding to Reform Judaism. or feminism, you know he just says
why not be more inclusive? So in terms of the מחיצה Mechitza
issue I have to tell you that I don't know as much.
I think in ספרדי Sefardi communities as a rule, you know women
don't come to שול shul as much. At least that's my sense.
I don't know if people have have you know, have knowledge about
that better than I do. So I think that maybe, you know
in some אשכנזי Ashkenazi שולן shuln also, like in Hungary or whatever,
they didn't have a מחיצה. Mechitza. You know why they didn't have
a מחיצה? Mechitza? Because women would never come to שול. shul. So
I don't know a full answer to that, but I'm I'm not
sure that here's where that difference would play out. But you are
absolutely correct that sometimes ironically ספרדים Sefardim see less problems where אשכנזים
Ashkenazim see problems in in these areas. So maybe what we'll do
because our time is coming up, again I don't know exactly, I
was told to to speak I think it was planned for an
hour. I'm happy to talk longer depending on what people want, but
maybe what I'll do is we'll just look at one or two
issues on the sources about this. We won't look about the question
about the women's section and does it have the same sanctity? I'll
leave that for you to look. But maybe in the second section
here that women as part of the ציבור Tzibur and how much
did we sort of want the women in שול shul or not
want the women in שול, shul, I think is interesting, so it
like relates to this. And we'll I'll just read one source from
this on page seven source number twelve and maybe we'll and maybe
we'll end with that source. Because that touches on this question about
sort of are women encouraged or expected to be in שול. shul.
And here's a question that was asked to רב הנקין, Rav Henkin,
so let's take a look. Somebody he says, לא ברור לי, Lo
barur li, as people see I'm on source twelve, source twelve, page
seven. לא ברור לי, Lo barur li, it's not clear to me
מה שכתב כבודו ma shekatav kevodo what you you what you wrote
to
me בשביל האמהות שחשקה נפשן להתפלל bishvil ha'imahot shechashkah nafshan lehitpallel that
there are women that want to come into שול shul and דאוון,
daven, ועל כן מביאים שמה את הילדים ve'al ken mevi'im shamah et
hayeladim and they bring the kids, שמפריעים shemafri'im and the kids are
causing a lot of noise and commotion and you basically want to
say that we should tell the women to stay home with the
kids because they're interrupt because it's leading to a lot of distractions.
So he says, טעות היא בדין, Ta'ut hi badin, כי עבור זה,
ki avur zeh, so you wrote that they're wrong to be coming
to שול, shul, כי עבור זה פטרה תורה את הנשים ממצות עשה
שהזמן גרמה, ki avur zeh patrah torah et hanashim mimitzvat aseh shehazman
gramah, that's why they're exempt, so that they should stay home with
the kids and not come to שול. shul. So he says,
אם כוונתו שנשים פטורות מתפילה סדורה, im kavanato shenashim peturot mitfilah sedurah,
if you're trying to say that women are exempt from regular דאוונינג,
davening, he says זה אינו, zeh eino, that's not true. They're not
exempt from דאוונינג, davening, but it's a larger attitude like women are
supposed to be home with the kids. And now if we look
at the next paragraph, he says,
ואם כוונתו, ve'im kavanato, if your intention is שהתורה פטרה אותן ממצות
עשה שהזמן גרמה כדי שתוכלנה להתעסק עם הטף, shehatorah patrah otan mimitzvat
aseh shehazman gramah kedei shetuchalnah lehit'asek im hataf, the reason they're exempt
from some מצוות Mitzvot is so that they could focus on child
rearing. ומזה תלמדנה, umizeh tilmadnah, and from this we should learn a
more general approach שאין היעוד שלהן לבוא לבית הכנסת דוקא, she'ein haye'ud
shelahen lavo leveit haknesset davka, their place is not in שול. shul.
שיכול להתפלל בבית, sheyachol lehitpallel babayit, let them stay at home and
be with the kids, don't come to שול. shul. So he says,
כשלעצמי, kshel'atzmi, by my personally I have to tell you, אני סבור
שכיוון שנשים היום יוצאות לכל דבר, ani savur shekeivan shenashim hayom yotz'ot
lechol davar, since nowadays women leave the go out of the house
for a million different reasons, right? They don't stay at home all
the time with the kids. הלוואי שתצאנה לבתי כנסיות ומקומות של קדושה,
halevai shetetze'nah levatei kneysiyot umekomot shel kedushah,
so of course we should, you know if only they would come
to שול. shul. Right? So we live in a different society. It's
not that women are at home full time and if women are
not at home full time, so of course, if anything, they should
be encouraged to be more participatory and come to שול. shul. וראוי
לעודדן, veraui le'odedan, we should encourage לבוא לבית הכנסת. lavo leveit haknesset.
So what do we do with the fact that of course that
they do bring the kids and the kids create commotion? So he
says, ואם חשקה נפשן לבוא לבית הכנסת, ve'im chashkah nafshan lavo leveit
haknesset, if they want to come to שול, shul, אז צריך להתייחס
לזה בכובד, az tzarich lehit'yaches lezeh bechoved, you have to treat it
seriously and with respect. ומבואר שכאשר רבות באות יש עגמת נפש לבודדות
להשאר בחוץ, umevo'ar sheka'asher rabot ba'ot yesh agmat nefesh levododot lehisha'er bachutz,
and he says not only that, this gets to the other point
about another form of egalitarianism. He says, you know that if that
if a lot of women are there, a few women that are
have to stay outside with the kids, they feel marginalized and excluded.
So he says, here's what you should do. וכל שבת אצלכם מתחזי
כזני, vechol shabbat etzelchem mitchazi kezani, every שבת Shabbat they come to
שול, shul, but they stay out of the outside with the kids.
ולכן לדעתי ראוי לסדר תורנות שמירת התינוקות כדי לאפשר לאימהות לבוא לבית
הכנסת. velachen ledati raui lesader toranut shmirat hatinokot kedei le'afsher le'imahot lavo
leveit haknesset.
So you should have a rotation. Okay? That's his solution. Now of
course it's still a rotation of the women, right? The other possibility
would be maybe the שול shul should use some funds to have
child care, right, so that everybody would be free to come to
the שול. shul. And I do have to say, and I think
this is an important point to end with because, you know these
issues are not just about sources and philosophy. I mean, they're they're
really a profound issue of a type of a sensitivity around these
things and how we, you know how much we are sort of
are aware of of how ingrained certain perspectives are. So for example,
you know often רבנים Rabbanim will say, right, well, you know like
if a woman says that she wants to do something to be
more participatory, it's like well, you
know if you
star, you know once you 8:45 or do you have the childcare
starting at 10:30? What are you doing that when the women are
there, they feel that they're more included rather than that they're spectators?
Right? So rather than saying, you know, oh, if you were to
show more, how much are we in subtle and not-so-subtle ways actually
putting people in a particular role and a box? And just to
give you one or two other examples of this, you know, I
had a student that once when he was
in the admissions interview for the ישיבה, Yeshiva, and he was talking
a little bit about his spiritual journey and what sensitized him to
some of these women's issues. He said, you know, once he and
his wife went into a שול shul to דאוון daven מנחה Mincha
or so, whatever it was, weekday, or passing by some שול. shul.
And then they walked out and his wife said to him, she
said, you never have to דאוון daven where the Hebrew writing is
reverse on your side of the מחיצה. mechitzah. You know what that
means? Ever see sometimes they have the glass and they have פסוקים
psukim written? You know, ever see that etched in? Which—who's it facing,
the etched in? The men, right? It's basically saying like, this is
for—for men. You—you know, you're there at our—at, you know, at our
leave. Or, I had a student that once was talking about where
we get the source of writing—of putting up in the שול shul
up at the top: דע לפני מי אתה עומד. Da Lifnei Mi
Atah Omed. You have that here? You don't? Okay. So anyway, he
was talking about this. He gave a whole little lecture about the
history of this. And I get up and I say, you know,
that was very fascinating. You spoke for seven minutes. You didn't stop
once to realize that that phrase is in the masculine. And what
does it say even if you're not thinking about it at a
subconscious level that you're seeing that phrase and what it's saying about
like who is the people that are being addressed and who are
not? So there's other things you can—some people do
דע לפני מי את/ה עומד/ת. Da Lifnei Mi At/He Omed/et. But the
easier thing is to put something like שויתי ה׳ לנגדי תמיד. Shiviti
Hashem Lenegdi Tamid. Right? There's some other things you could put up
there that don't send the same type of a message. And it
really is about developing a sensitivity around these issues and about involving
people in the discussion. You know, about the rabbi not just dictating
ex cathedra, even if the rabbi's trying to be sensitive, you know,
but so much about—about involving men and women, women and men in
the conversations and in the discussion so that really, you know, things
can be done in the most inclusive and sensitive way. But it
requires a lot of, you know, sensitivity and orient—and a reorientation to
start thinking about this way because sadly in many ways it is
ingrained like that this is a male space. One other example and
then with that I'll end. Did you ever have a case where
the rabbi says something like,
you know, well, we're not going to—we're going to first wait for
everybody to, you know, to put away their טלית tallit and תפילין?
tefillin? Or everybody to put away their טלית, tallit, right? It's not
everybody. It's the men. But—but by saying everybody, in a way it's
again sort of saying the—these are the everybody that I am thinking
about in terms of who really the audience is. I keep on
coming up with more examples. I'll give you one last—one last of
the last examples is, and this is something we are very careful
about at the—at the ישיבה, Yeshiva, is—is that very often if in—if
there's a weekday דאוונינג davening and there's a מחיצה mechitzah and there's
no women there, the men will sort of spill over into the
women's side and they'll use the women's side to put on their
תפילין tefillin and טלית tallit or whatever. And then if a woman
comes, so they'll move away and they'll make space for her. But
the message that sends is fundamentally this is all our space, right?
If we have to, we'll cede some of this space, we'll be
gracious enough to cede some of this space to you. In the
ישיבה, Yeshiva, we are very careful that even though it's a ישיבה
Yeshiva of all guys
and—and, you know, it's—at most like one or two women sometimes will
come to the דאוונינג, davening, before we do any דאוונינג, davening, we
put the מחיצה mechitzah straight down the middle and it is completely
forbidden for any man to walk on the woman's side. I don't
care if he needs to get a ספר, sefer, I don't care
if he's coming in the other door. You don't come in the
other door. You know, that space has to remain, you know, sort
of off-limits. That has to remain fully a woman's space so women
should always feel that they have an equal portion in being as
part of the דאוונינג, davening, you know, as men. So there's a
lot of areas and that—מחיצה mechitzah is a central one, but there's
a lot of areas that we need to really sensitize ourselves to
this and really a lot of it is involving everybody in the
conversation and in the process. And with that, I actually will end.
So. Thank you.
Yes.
So—so in your last example, that's actually according to...